Alright, okay, מועד טוב. Moet Tov. Today's דף Daf is ק"יב, Kuf
Yud Bet, and we pick up from בעא מיניה Ba'a minei רב
דימי מרב נחמן Rav Dimi mi-Rav Nachman on the last thing we
had done yesterday on שבת Shabbos was the whole discussion about נ"ט
בר נ"ט. Nat Bar Nat. I was asked to start today with
a brief summary of how we פוסקים pasken about that להלכה. l'halacha.
We had done נ"ט בר נ"ט Nat Bar Nat and the knife,
some of the few lines of גמרא Gemara some very critical things
להלכה. l'halacha. So let me quickly summarize that before we begin the
דף. Daf. So as you saw, it says דגים שעלו בקערה מותר
לאכלן בכותח, dagim she'alah bekara mutar le'ochlan bekutach, that is if you
put fish in a plate, a hot פליישיג fleishig plate, or the
fish is hot, then nevertheless the fish are not really considered פליישיג.
fleishig. It's נ"ט בר נ"ט, Nat Bar Nat, the פליישיג fleishig into
the plate, the plate into the fish, and it's still היתר, heter,
and therefore you can eat it with milk. That's called נ"ט בר
נ"ט דהיתרא, Nat Bar Nat de-Hetera, two degrees removed and it's still
היתר. heter. Now the first thing just to realize that that is
distinguished from נ"ט בר נ"ט דאיסורא. Nat Bar Nat de-Issura. The whole
reason you can't use what we use טריף treif כלים, kelim, right,
once into the... if you use this pot's חזיר, chazir, חזיר chazir
to pot, pot into your food, נ"ט בר נ"ט. Nat Bar Nat.
So the point is, נ"ט בר נ"ט דאיסורא Nat Bar Nat de-Issura
when it's בדיעבד bidieved is not acceptable. It's only acceptable when you're
dealing with היתר, heter, מילכיגס milchigs or פליישיגס, fleishigs, because then we
say the logic presumably is that once something has a status of
forbidden, that status, the הלכתי halachic status and I think they called
this before the stickiness factor, so it sticks and stays. If it
has no status, מילכיגס milchigs or פליישיגס fleishigs by itself is היתר,
heter, has no status yet until it comes in contact with the
other type. So
therefore it can become... if the taste is weakened both practically and
הלכתית, halachically, it's two degrees removed from the original. א, A, it
might just be not as tasteable, what the גמרא Gemara indicated, but
also it might be just two degrees removed and distant from the
original taste. Therefore it has no status. Now, the other qualification also
is that that's only if at the second stage it still is
היתר. heter. Let's say you have פליישיג fleishig into the pot and
then you cook milk in the pot. That's a מפורש ברייתא, meforash
braisa, קדירה שבישל בה בשר אסור לבשל בה חלב, k'deira she-bishal bah
basar assur le-vashel bah chalav, that you can't cook milk in a
pot that you cooked meat in, because there at the second נ"ט
Nat from the pot into what you're cooking, you're getting meat and
milk at the second stage. So נ"ט בר נ"ט דהיתרא Nat Bar
Nat de-Hetera is only היתר, heter, only מילכיגס milchigs or פליישיגס fleishigs
by itself and only if at the second stage it is still
היתר. heter. So basically what happens when you cook פרווה parve things
in מילכיג milchig or פליישיג fleishig pots? You know the DE, the
dairy equipment, or you cook noodles in a פליישיג fleishig pot or
in a מילכיג milchig pot. Right, what is the status? So the
גמרא Gemara says not a problem, at that stage it's already נ"ט
בר נ"ט Nat Bar Nat and it's still היתר, heter, go ahead
and eat it in the other thing. Do we actually פוסקים pasken
this way? If we did פוסקים pasken this way, why would people
have strings about running DE, dairy equipment on, and why they go
so far to write dairy on it? So the story is like
this: we do פוסקים pasken it, but the but is that רש"י,
Rashi, based on a רש"י Rashi and תוספות, Tosafot, what there is
is a whole discussion about maybe it's worse. Maybe the גמרא Gemara
is only because it wasn't real cooking. Maybe the גמרא Gemara is
only because it was putting dry hot fish on a dry plate.
But if you actually did it over a fire, maybe that transfers
the taste more directly and it's not considered two degrees removed but
only one degree removed. That's one question. However, they say maybe if
it was cooked that although it's on the fire on the one
hand, since there's water, the water makes it three degrees from the
pot to the water to the thing. So maybe we need to
be more stringent on fire, but maybe we can qualify
that
stringency, thank you, not stringiness,
stringency, if it's cooked with water etc. These are the questions. So
the upshot basically is the following: if you are doing it directly
over fire, for
אשכנזים, Ashkenazim, לכתחילה lechatchila don't do it with intent to mix with
the other thing, and don't לכתחילה lechatchila mix it with the other
thing. So I'm cooking noodles in my פליישיג fleishig pot, or let's
make it the other... people like to put meat sauce on their
noodles. I'm cooking noodles in my מילכיג milchig pot. If I am
planning on making noodles
and spaghetti and meatballs, I'm not allowed to. I'm not allowed to
use my מילכיג milchig pot if I'm planning on doing spaghetti and
meatballs. If I'm not planning on doing spaghetti and meatballs and I'm
just cooking them in my מילכיג milchig pot and then I have
them and I say, "Oh my God, I forgot I cooked in
my מילכיג milchig pot I want to use it for spaghetti and
meatballs," can I do that? So the אשכנזים, Ashkenazim, it's funny what
you say, אשכנזים Ashkenazim would still say no, don't do it לכתחילה,
lechatchila, because maybe cooking over a fire maybe it doesn't go down
a level. So you can't eat them together. What if I didn't
realize and I already put the meat sauce on top of the
noodles?
Not in the pot I mean, on a plate.
On my plate, I put out the meat and noodles and now
I mix them. I'm not supposed to mix it but I now
mixed it. Then even אשכנזים Ashkenazim would say you already mixed them
and now you'd have to throw it out? Fine, it's okay, it
was נ"ט בר נ"ט דהיתרא. Nat Bar Nat de-Hetera. ספרדים Sefardim by
the way would say it's מותר לכתחילה mutar lechatchila as long as
they didn't do it with that in mind. Okay, so that's the
basic הלכה. halacha. If you actually don't eat it together לכתחילה, lechatchila,
if you mixed it then you can go ahead and eat it.
Now let's say I was told not to eat it לכתחילה. lechatchila.
What does
it, what so... What can I do? So what I will tell
people to do is, by the way, if you eat something made
in dairy equipment, or מילכיג milchig *milchig* equipment, it doesn't, פליישיג fleishig
*fleishig* equipment, it doesn't make you פליישיג fleishig *fleishig*. It doesn't make
you מילכיג milchig, *milchig*. That everybody agrees. So if I eat something
that was eaten in meat equipment and it's פרווה *parve*, right, I
want to eat potatoes that were cooked in a meat pot that
was פרווה *parve*, so I'm not פליישיג fleishig *fleishig*. Okay. So what
I will tell people is you're not allowed to eat it together,
but people who actually ask me, I've made it for this meal
and I want to serve, you know, the other thing at the
meal, I've made it for, you know, I had noodles, it's going
to be plain noodles or whatever with some olive oil or whatever,
but I want to serve it at a meal that has פליישיגס
fleishigs, *fleishigs*. Okay. Am I allowed to? So I say, yeah, as
long as you don't mix it together. So you just have to
be careful that you first, you know, you can have both on
your plate, don't mix them together, maybe you have to be, maybe
it's safer, spaghetti meatballs and spaghetti, maybe it's safer to have a
separate plate, but whatever, just so they don't get mixed together. I
guess if inadvertently they get mixed together, בדיעבד bedieved *bedieved* it's okay,
just לכתחילה lechatchila *lechatchila* you can't. And you have some spaghetti, and
then you can have some meatballs, or you have some more spaghetti,
and then you can have some more meatballs, or whatever you're adding,
your spaghetti and then your chicken, and then you have your spaghetti,
you're just not allowed to mix them together. I'm sure some people
wouldn't be happy with that, they would feel that that's too close
for comfort, but really, technically you are allowed to do that. And
otherwise it means you're not going to be able to use this
dish for your meal, then I will actually, you know, that's okay.
The other thing to note is, this is all when the כלים
*keilim* were בן יומו *ben yomo*. When the כלים *keilim* were not
בן יומו *ben yomo*, right, then it's, then not only of course
then anything goes, you can use a non-kosher piece of meat, but
not only that, if it's not בן יומו *ben yomo* according to
the גר"א *Gra*, לכתחילה lechatchila, *lechatchila* you can, if it's נ"ט בר
נ"ט דהיתירא *nat bar nat de-heteira* and not בן יומו *ben yomo*,
you can cook it for the other thing. So if I want
to cook spaghetti for my spaghetti and meatballs meal, and the only,
the best pot I've got is my big מילכיג *milchig* pot, okay,
right, can I use my מילכיג *milchig* pot to cook my spaghetti
and meatballs? According to the גר"א *Gra*, the answer is, if that
pot is not a בן יומו *ben yomo*, go ahead, לכתחילה *lechatchila*.
You can even לכתחילה *lechatchila* do it to make the spaghetti to
cook for the other, for the other thing. If it's נ"ט בר
נ"ט *nat bar nat* combined with אינו בן יומו aino ben yomo,
*eino ben yomo*, you can even do it לכתחילה *lechatchila*. So that
is a רגל אחת *regel achat* summary of נ"ט בר נ"ט *nat
bar nat*. There was a question.
Yes, so I'm going back to that vegetarian liver, if that was
made in a כלי *keili*, a meat כלי *keili*. Right. So I
could have it with a meal where there's dairy as long as
I just eat it separately.
Right. And that's by the way what's crazy about, about the fact
that the OU is so concerned that oh my god, you're not
going to know the הלכות halachot *halachos* of dairy equipment, we have
to call it dairy. What in the end of the day is
the big deal about the dairy equipment? If you went ahead and
actually accidentally mixed it with the meat, בדיעבד bedieved. *bedieved* you would
be allowed to eat it. You know, there's a general principle in
הלכה halacha. *halacha* that something that בדיעבד *bedieved* is okay, we don't
make גזירות *gezeiros* about. Okay. So here the OU made their own
גזירה *gezeira*. You won't understand the הלכות halachos *halachos* of dairy equipment,
so because we're afraid we're going to make a גזירה *gezeira* and
call it dairy. But the point is בדיעבד *bedieved* dairy equipment even
if you mixed it with the other thing, בדיעבד *bedieved* it's all
okay anyway. So that's taking things a little overboard.
I used בדיעבד *bedieved* a lot of times today. Yes, and you
didn't use it a lot of times.
Well that's true.
Yes, I used one for the other. Uh-huh, uh-huh. So you did
that.
You used one for the other?
In a lot of things, one for the other.
Very interesting. Even when it was a בן יומו *ben yomo*?
Yeah, and other people were poor.
Right. They lived on the road in the business, plastic cutlery.
Right, very interesting.
They had to כשר kasher *kasher* the pot every two weeks, switch
it
over, switch it over.
Very interesting, very interesting.
Everything was
good.
Right, right. But in your case really, like taking the spaghetti and
then taking the meatball, you should be careful to first chew it
first.
Yeah, better it's sitting in your mouth, right, yeah, but you don't
have to worry about like the grease in your mouth like you
would between the whole מילכיגס milchigs *milchigs* and פליישיגס fleishigs. *fleishigs*. Right,
I mean you don't have to like take some bread. Exactly, you
don't have to do a, what's it called, a הדחה *hadacha*. Okay,
so that's the standing on one foot נ"ט בר נ"ט *nat bar
nat*, and now we'll give you standing on one foot knife issues.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says by the knife, the knife, the
דבר חריף davar charif *davar charif*. The דבר חריף davar charif *davar
charif* here was also two lines, right, you cut the צנון tznon
*tson*, the radish. So what's the story? So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
was concerned that it absorbs the taste and so on and it's
a problem. So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*, first of all, there's a whole
question, are we assuming a clean knife or a dirty knife? The
simple פשט *pshat* here is that we're assuming a dirty knife. There's
indications that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* basically assumed that the knives were
serrated and it was hard to get clean, so they were, we
have to, and they were greasy, we have to assume, they were
assuming a dirty knife. Part of the evidence is that the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says that if you alternate between cutting the צנון tznon
*tson* and cutting other types of things, it's not a problem. If
the knife was clean and the question was the power of the
דבר חריף davar charif *davar charif* of the radish to pull the
absorbed taste out, why would it matter if I used this knife
to cut, you know, bread or to cut normal vegetables? How would
that affect the hidden absorbed taste? So the simple פשט *pshat* is
that it's a dirty knife. And if it's a dirty knife, then
it's a concern that the taste gets transferred, and by צנון tznon
*tson* maybe it's not just on the surface and washing isn't enough.
We discussed before, did we do that גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* already about
if it's cold and the wash, you can wash it off? Yeah,
yeah, that was the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. of course right? So, so
okay, maybe it's not just on the surface, it's a little bit
on the inside, it's known as powerful, and that's if it's a
dirty knife. תוספות Tosafot reinforces that because תוספות Tosafot says, you know,
if even using heat, נת בר נת דהיתירא, nat bar nat deheteira,
you know, isn't a problem of getting it out, how where's the
power of this צנון more than heat, and if you used it
with a פליישיג fleishig knife all of a sudden this צנון is
a problem, but trumping you did on heat with a not, you
know, with a פליישיג fleishig thing is not a problem. So therefore
the simplest explanation of all of this is that it's a dirty
knife and if it's a clean knife it's a non-issue. However, there
is there is a reading of this גמרא Gemara that even if
the knife is clean the power of the צנון is such, of
דבר חריף davar charif, is such that it pulls out the absorbed
taste, and not only does it pull it out without heat, but
it even pulls it out that it doesn't go down a level
to a נת בר נת, nat bar nat, and that is at
least לכתחילה how we פסקן, pasken, or not even לכתחילה, that is
the basic פסק psak of the שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, that the
power of a דבר חריף davar charif, is that even if it's
פליישיג fleishig, to מילכיג it pulls it out without heat and it
doesn't go down a level of נת בר נת. nat bar nat.
Then you add another גמרא, Gemara so if you consider whatever the
knife is, פליישיג or מילכיג, you add another גמרא Gemara in עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah that talks about a specific type of a one
thing, a קורטיא דחילתית, kurtia de-chiltis, a very sharp item, and that
says that there they use the phrase it makes things, fat things
taste good, and then if you conflated it all, you wind up
saying that a דבר חריף davar charif not only pulls it out
and doesn't go down a level, but it will even do it
to something that's an אינו בן יומו, aino ben yomo it'll even
do it to something that's more than a day old. And there
you combine all of the most stringent readings of all the גמראס
Gemaras and say that it's all talking about the same דבר חריף,
davar charif and you get to the point that if you have
a פליישיג knife totally clean last used, you know, six weeks ago
and you cut your radish or your onion with it, that your
radish or your onion is considered פליישיג, even though it's an אינו
בן יומו it doesn't matter because it's a דבר חריף, davar charif
even though it's clean the power of the onion pulls out the
taste that's absorbed in the knife and even though it's נת בר
נת דהיתירא nat bar nat deheteira somehow the power of a דבר
חריף davar charif? keeps it all at the one-nat level. So that
is, you know, all of the all the big issues we have
about דבר חריף come from the stringent readings of all those גמראס
Gemaras and combining them. Whether, you know, what types of leniencies are
available בדיעבד is a separate conversation but as you can see there's
not the only reads of those גמראס Gemaras so there are some,
you know, there are some options בדיעבד.
Is there like a short list of what a דבר חריף is?
No, you know, the גמרא Gemara mentions here the radish, you'd add
to that things like onions, garlic and whatever those types of things,
and salt gets added but is salt really the same as דבר
חריף? So no, let's that's enough for הלכה. halacha Now let's get
back to the גמרא. Gemara Okay serious, all right so בעי מיניה,
bai minei, now to finally start the actual גמרא Gemara today's דף,
daf, four lines down on קי"ב ע"א. kuf yud beis amud aleph.
בעי מיניה רב דימי מרב נחמן, bai minei Rav Dimi me-Rav Nachman,
Rav Dimi asked Rav Nachman, מהו להניח כדא דמילחא גבי כדא דכמחא,
mahu lehaniach kada de-milcha gabi kada de-kimcha,
can you put your, your vessel, your dish of salt near your
dish of כמחא? kimcha? כמחא kimcha was their כותח, kutaich, was their
sort of sour milk dip. Now the point is this was, you
know, some people have this still nowadays, not a salt shaker but
a little salt salt dish, you know, that you use your hand
and you sprinkle salt with it. So he wanted to know can
you have them next to each other because the concern was is
that they're both open dishes, you dip into both of them accidentally
there might be some transfer and then what happens is that some
of your sourdough will dip into your, or not sourdough, some of
your sour milk dip, whatever your כותח kutaich will fall into your
salt and then you're going to use the same salt dish for
מילכיגס and פליישיגס, and then you're going to use it on your,
you know, and it'll get into your פליישיגס.
So, so אמר ליה אסור, amar lei assur, it's forbidden. דחלא מאי,
dechala mai, how about if it's not, if it's, I'm using vinegar
an open dipping dish of vinegar near my כותח, kutaich, what's the
story? אמר ליה שרי, amar lei shari, it's permissible. ומאי שנא, u-mai
shena, why is one different than the other? So he said דכי
תכיל לי קורא דמילחא, de-chi tachil li kora de-milcha, so this was
a phrase which, which means basically which says, well, when you measure
out for me some salt I'll tell it to you, which was
an idiomatic phrase which means like either you know work a little
harder, think a little harder, you know, it's like if somebody's asking
a question, if somebody asks a question, but of course here it's
a little bit of a play because it's talking about using a
salt dish. Anyway מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, so what is the reason?
האי איתא איסורא בהא והא ליתא איסורא בהא, hai ita issura be-hai
ve-hai leita issura be-hai, because even though interestingly there might be some
transfer, if there is transfer into the salt dish from this, from
this כותח, kutaich, it'll be בהא, be-hai, you know, if you have
a little dripping of yogurt let's say on top of your salt
it'll stay there the yogurt and then you're going to take from
it and put onto your meat you'll have yogurt in your meat.
If however a little yogurt drips into your vinegar it'll dissolve and
get mixed up and the assumption is also that it will become
בטל, batel, that it'll be a trivial amount that will drip in
a huge amount of vinegar so it'll be בטל batel and therefore
it won't be a problem even if that happens. Okay so here's
the principle that even if you have a large amount of something
it won't affect ביטול bitul if the other retains its identity, you
know, is distinct, doesn't get dissolved and mixed in. And that's why
it's a problem. Okay. ההוא בר גוזלא דנפל לכדא דתמכא. Hahu bar
gozla denafal lakada detimcha. Now there was a third there was a
pigeon that fell into a shocheted dish, that fell into a pitcher
of this כותח, kutach, you know, we'll call it yogurt. So here
you go, meat and milk together. So it gives no heat. Normally
you need some type of heat to affect transfer. So let's take
a look. שריא רב הונא רב חיננא בריה דרב מפרשניא. Sharya Rav
Huna Rav Chinana brei deRav miParshunya. So Rav Chinana permitted it. אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, said Rava, מן חכים למישרי כי האי גוונא אי
לאו רב חיננא בריה דרב מפרשניא. Man chakim lemishrei ki hai gavna
i lav Rav Chinana brei deRav miParshunya. Who would have been so
smart to figure out how you could מותר muttar this were it
not Rabbi Chinana? Now why would it have taken being smart? Because
this chicken had been salted, right? I mean how you get you
know that's what you do with all meat, you salt it. So
presumably it fell in after it had been right after it had
been plucked and salted and fell in. So why doesn't the fact
that it was salted a problem about saltiness is like heat? We
learned about it before, מליח כרותח. maliach keroteach. Why doesn't that cause
absorption? כסבר, Kasavar, because he is of the opinion, כי אמר שמואל
מליח הרי הוא כרותח, Ki amar Shmuel maliach harei hu keroteach, when
did Shmuel say salted is like boiled,
is like heat? הני מילי היכא דאינו נאכל מחמת מלחו. Hani mili
heicha de'eino ne'echal machamat milcho. That's only if it can't be eaten
as a result of its saltiness. אבל האי, Aval hai, but this,
האי כותחא, hai kutcha, I'm sorry I excuse me I said that
the chicken was salted but or the pigeon but actually it was
you know at least that's how the גמרא Gemara is focusing and
the גמרא Gemara is focusing on that the yogurt actually or whatever
this dip had salt in it too. So האי כותחא, hai kutcha,
this כותח, kutach, הרי נאכל מחמת מלחו, harei ne'echal machamat milcho, actually
can be eaten as a result of its saltiness. It is salty
but it's edible. Now what why would you have something so salty
that it wouldn't be edible? So the answer is what? Well you
mean to get the A to get the blood out, that salt
that's still sitting there if you haven't rinsed it off. And B
because if you don't have refrigerators that's how you preserve your meat
is you bury them in salt. So that's what רש"י Rashi says.
רש"י Rashi says what we're talking about a saltiness to the degree
that it is so heavily salted that that's how you preserve your
meat and only and it would only be considered to be a
problem you know if you rinsed off only then would it be
would it be the מליח כרותח. maliach keroteach. So according to רש"י
Rashi you will almost never have a practical issue of מליח כרותח
maliach keroteach certainly for us nowadays because we never salt things that
heavily. תוספות Tosafot disagree. תוספות Tosafot says it's already considered אינו נאכל
מחמת מלחו, eino ne'echal machamat milcho, it doesn't have to be that
heavily salted, that completely inedible. Up to you would eat to the
point by the way that you wouldn't eat your meat in that
state if you had salted it to preserve it you would rinse
off the salt before eating it. But when it was in that
state according to רש"י Rashi that was the degree of saltiness. תוספות
Tosafot says no it doesn't have to be that salty.
תוספות Tosafot says פשיטא pshita even if it's the amount of saltiness
of מלח קדרונית melach kadronit in order to כשר kasher it. Even
there that's too heavily salted for normal people to eat it. That
is מליח כרותח. maliach keroteach. And we basically rule like תוספות Tosafot
and that's the amount of saltiness we worry for. Of course it
doesn't end with תוספות Tosafot because as you all remember the Ashkenazi
approach is keep it simple stupid. So therefore since who knows how
salty is אינו נאכל מחמת מלחו eino ne'echal machamat milcho we have
to be strict for all saltiness. Now it doesn't really mean all
saltiness meaning a trivial amount of salt that we normally put to
spice the food is not a problem. But once it starts getting
seriously salty we are strict and we're concerned that that might be
considered מליח כרותח maliach keroteach and might effect transfer. I want to
say another thing about this idea about the salt and getting out
the blood because it came up a little bit yesterday and we're
going to see it a little bit tomorrow about the whole idea
of salting meat which interestingly by the way is not in any
of the משניות. Mishnayot. If you notice the גמרא Gemara. finds a
way to get into discussing the whole get into the liver and
the getting out the blood and the salting but it's not in
any of the משניות Mishnayot which is bizarre and I have yet
to figure out an answer for that. But anyway תוספות Tosafot often
quotes a בה"ג Bahag about the effect of salt on meat to
explain this idea of מליח כרותח. maliach keroteach. Because the question is
like this: you put salt on your meat to כשר kasher it
to get out the blood. How long do you have to wait
for all the blood to get out? Who knows? The גמרא Gemara
never says. So the בה"ג Bahag says you know how long you
wait? You wait as long as it would take for if you
were roasting the meat over an open fire for the heat to
draw out the blood. What's the comparison? One is heat one is
salt. So the comparison is no no Shmuel says salt מליח כרותח,
maliach keroteach, salt works like heat. So says the בה"ג Bahag that
that also explains why salting gets out the blood. Now we know
the reason salt gets out the blood is because of osmosis, right?
But the בה"ג Bahag says that's the principle of Shmuel that salt
is like heat. So since it's working like heat if it takes
15 minutes over an open fire for the blood to come out
then with salt which is working like heat it takes 15 minutes
for the blood to come out. Because of that equation תוספות Tosafos
uses that to teach a lot of הלכות about the saltiness that
transfers takes and that's why תוספות Tosafos says you see according to
that בה"ג. Bahag. The saltiness that transfers taste is the saltiness that
you do for kashering meat. That is the amount of salt that
is equivalent to heat, that's why it kashers and that's why with
that amount of salt taste can transfer. So this is the principle
of מליח כרותח Maliach k'roseach which we'll see more about tomorrow or
even later today, I forget, a little yeah basically tomorrow, but according
to תוספות Tosafos... it is the saltiness that you same amount of
salt that you use to kasher meat. You had a question Charlie.
Yeah, I was going to ask about is it the same standard
for everybody? Even today there are people who can't eat salted meat
because of health problems. Yeah, no, the גמרא Gemara would not be
talking about that. I mean it wasn't talking about your personal stuff.
It was talking about like a degree a certain like a standard
idea.
So you're saying although תוספות Tosafos don't really תוספות...
Tosafot Well we're even more מחמיר, machmir, yeah. But that's always the
way we are.
Not always, but you have to roast the meat to extract the
blood.
Right, so that's yeah it's always one of those you know that
begs the next question and that was actually the question yesterday the
גמרא Gemara said, right? That was the question yesterday. Right, גמרא Gemara,
sees that how do you know and you know maybe the top
piece and not the bottom piece, right? So you know but the
point is is that they had some accepted standard by the time
that you know this is this is also why it's funny like
all of those details about how do you exactly remove the fat,
how do you exactly salt the meat, the גמרא Gemara doesn't discuss
because this was all sort of you know part of the mimetic
tradition and it's things that you know it's much easier to learn
by practice than actually to describe by doing. So the בה"ג Bahag
was assuming that there was a known amount of time that you
roast the meat for, but right he never spells that out but
that did come up yesterday. How do you know when the blood
has stopped coming out of the meat?
So that's perfectly acceptable that's the word just like you have to
kasher a liver by by
roasting it, you could do that with meat also instead of salting
that's if if you were so inclined.
Well that was yesterday's גמרא. Gemara Yeah, yeah, right, exactly. And okay,
all right, the bigger question is whether you can salt a liver
and that you know תוספות Tosafot thinks you can but he says
it says at the end he quotes the רי"ף Rif that says
you know מנהג כלל ישראל minhag Klal Yisrael is never is only
to roast liver not to salt.
So that's how they kasher roast by roasting it?
Yeah. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, go on.
Okay, והני מילי חי. v'hani mili chai. Now when is this true
that it's not a problem this pigeon that fell into the כותח?
kutach? If it was raw. אבל צלי, aval tzli, if it was
roasted, בעי קליפה, bei klipa, you have to remove a shell. I'll
talk about that in a minute. ואי אית ביה פילי, v'ei is
bei pili, and if it has crevices and cracks, כולי אסור, kulei
assur, it's all forbidden. Now what does this mean roasted? So some
say it means roasted and hot and then you have the heat
transferring the taste. Okay, and this says even though only one of
them is hot, the top thing a hot chicken fell into
yogurt or whatever, but even if one of them is hot at
least it gets into an outer shell and you have to peel
off the outer shell. However, another very reasonable read of this גמרא
Gemara is that we're not talking about it's hot though, but what
we're talking is is that once something is roasted it is more
absorbent. And even though we normally say that you need heat to
transfer taste, let me give you an example. You need heat to
transfer taste, very nice. Let's say you had a nice soft piece
of טשולנט cholent meat, okay, and it was not hot and it
fell into a and it fell into a
pitcher of milk and it sat there for six hours. Would you
say oh no heat no problem just wash it off? I hope
you wouldn't, right? You would understand that that was highly absorbent and
it absorbed milk even if it did not sort of transfer by
taste, it transferred by the milk getting into the crevices. Even if
it was cold. So if you would, the milk didn't what?
That's כבוש. kavush. That's one that's one.
That's כבוש kavush but כבוש kavush is only 24 hours and כבוש
kavush is whatever. This is purely because of the absorbency of the
thing in it. So that is one way that the first that
this idea of צלי tzli is understood. Not that it's hot, but
once it's roasted then the meat is absorbent. And if the meat
is absorbent at least we have to be afraid that a little
of the liquid got into the outer shell. And then it goes
on to say and if there are crevices in it like the
example I gave you like that piece of טשולנט cholent meat, you
know that's not like you know you understand the difference right a
normal piece has just like you know a smooth shell but there's
other that are really very absorbent they have a lot of crevices.
Then we have to assume that even if it's cold you know
it got through all of it and the whole thing is forbidden.
Now there are those that read that this is only with heat.
But I think that you know
as I tell my students you can't ignore the מציאות. metzius. Very
nice to learn all these הלכות about heat and יד סולדת בו
yad soledes bo and so on, but then to say oh it
was all cold and so if something really absorbent fell into something
else it's going it's taking you know it's going a little bit
too far about you know rooting in the world of הלכה Halacha
and not a world of reality. And I think that's what this
גמרא Gemara is saying and that's at least a number of ראשונים
Rishonim that understand that it's totally without heat but if it's something
that's absorbent then obviously we assume that the milk got in. Okay.
So how long do you say it
takes to absorb though?
That's always that's a question. You know as you're right that we
should be
talking about מציאות metzius then.
Right, exactly. No, the other approach would
say keep it simple so then the moment it fell in you
say it's not it's not.
Yeah, I'm not sure with the combination of it being cold. With
heat we do say that by the way, even though also by
heat you
have... But you know, by heat we actually do say it's basically
instantaneous, and by cold it may, you know, maybe of a little
bit more of a latitude to try to assess based on a
מציאות. Metzius. ואם תבלו בתבלין Ve'im tavlu betavlin if it is spiced
with spices, even if it doesn't have a lot of crevices, כולי
עלמא אסור Kulei alma assur it's also forbidden because presumably that creates,
you know, absorbency, right? I mean that's the same osmosis idea of
the salt, isn't that? Is it? Help me here, guys. I forgot
my high school biology. But what's the osmosis principle of the salt
that causes the blood to go out?
Is that because the blood is less salty
and you want to equate the salt concentration on both sides? Yeah.
So similarly, if you have meat that's spicy or salty in a
liquid, it's going to pull liquid in. Right, so that's the basic
point. So if it's very spicy, then that will, or especially if
it's salty, I don't know if it would be true if it's
spicy without being salty. Does similar osmosis principles work?
Spices are bigger molecules. I don't know if that will work. Okay.
So anyway, but
at least the same principle is what even after you rinsed off
the salt, the meat is still salt more salty.
Right. So and if it's very salt spicy here, the גמרא, Gemara
it certainly works if it's salty, then also you have to be
concerned for greater absorption. Okay.
Even if it's חי? Chai?
Yes, presumably. Well, not clear. It might be combined with צלי. Tzali.
Right. It might be, yeah, right, right. Presumably combined with צלי. Tzali.
Okay. אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel. Said
Rav Nachman in the name of Shmuel. So now we're doing a
lot of practical הלכה as you can see. כיכרא דחתיך עליה בשרא
אסור למיכליה. Kichra dechatich alei bisra assur lemichlei.
If you cut meat on a piece of bread, then you can't
eat it. Why? Because now we're back to the blood. We're afraid
that the act of cutting, some juices run off of the piece
of meat, get absorbed into the bread, and that juice we're afraid
is blood that has not been removed from the meat in the
original process of salting or roasting. So it's not really just that,
you know, we usually find that like cutting it on my plate,
right, and it runs into my carrots or my rice. But that
red stuff that comes off when you cut your piece of meat,
he said was still blood.
Now, if you really think that there's still blood in it, why
are you allowed to eat the meat itself? So the answer is,
here's the secret, and this goes back to the whole previous גמרא
Gemara that you did yesterday, is that as long as that blood
has not come out of the meat, it is considered permissible. It's
called דמא דאברים שלא פירש, Dama de'evarim shelo peirash, blood that's absorbed
in the actual meat itself, right? It's not like in a vein
or something, or it's not in the heart. It's absorbed in the
meat itself. I mean, obviously we know that meat has tiny little,
you know, blood vessels that are going through it, but they're not
visible. So for all intents and purposes, absorbed in the meat itself,
it is not forbidden blood until it comes out. So that's why
you could actually eat meat totally raw without הכשר Kashering it. That's
also why, by the way, the issue of roasting is not necessarily
that roasting gets out all the blood. Even if roasting did not
get out all the blood, whatever is left in never left the
piece of meat, then it's permissible. You can't do that with cooking,
because if you cook a piece of meat that hasn't had all
the blood come out, the blood, what happens in the cooking process?
Goes out and goes back in. But in roasting, the stuff that
goes out stays out, the stuff that's in stays in. So actually,
technically speaking, you could roast a piece of meat and have it
like rare or medium-rare and not take out all the blood. So
here, the first statement here is that if you have a piece
of meat and you're cutting it and red juices are coming off,
that's still blood. It didn't come out originally. If it's still in
the meat, it's fine. Once it came out, it's forbidden. And you
can't eat that juice that runs off.
Wait, same principle as milk in the udder?
Same principle as milk in the udder, exactly. That the milk in
the udder, as long as it hasn't left, it's okay, but once
it leaves, then it becomes a problem. Then it's treated as milk.
That is correct. There it's easier, there it's דרבנן, Derabbanan, because there
חלב שחוטה Chalav shechuta is דרבנן. Derabbanan. But here even biblical, right,
even דאורייתא De'oraisa blood, same principle.
Just to make sure I understand. So let's say, you know, you
go to the butcher and you buy that piece of chicken that's
raw and you still see like a little bit of the blood,
you know, in the package, you know what I'm talking about, like
sometimes it's a little bit juicy? So that
if you cut that on a piece of bread, you couldn't eat
the bread? Is that what we're talking about?
No, that juice, if you see red juice, but if it's been
salted and he's saying that even after it's been salted or roasted,
any additional red juice is still blood and it's still forbidden.
Right, so you can't cut that chicken then on your bread, right?
If more juice were to come out. Right. I mean, maybe all
the juice has already come out. Right. So let's take a look
though. The גמרא Gemara doesn't end here.
אסור למיכליה. Assur lemichlei. והני מילי דאסמיק. Ve'hanei mili de'asmik. That's only
if this juice that comes out is red. והני מילי דעבראי. Ve'hanei
mili de'avrai. And that's only that it appeared
that it was so much that it went through the whole thickness
of the bread.
והני מילי דאפמיכי Ve'hanei mili de'afmichi only if it's thick. So not
all stuff, some stuff is just gravy, reddish gravy. But if it's
thick and it's so much that it goes all the way through
the piece of bread, then you have to be concerned that it's
still blood. אבל קלישא aval klisha if it's thin, if it's you
know and not so thick, לית לן בה leit lan bah that's
not a problem.
Like to my example would be, okay, right.
Right. Now
Shmuel, if this happened where it got onto the bread, apparently this
was a common thing to cut, they didn't have cutting boards, to
cut on bread, so then Shmuel would just throw it to his
dog. Okay? Because he couldn't eat it but of course the dog's
gonna like it. רב הונא יהיב ליה לשמעיה. Rav Huna yahiv lei
leshamaei. Now Rav Huna gave
it to his to his attendant. Now the attendants were Jewish, so
now they're going to ask the obvious question: if it's not kosher
enough for you but it's kosher enough for him, so ממה נפשך
mima nafshach make up your mind. אי שרי לכולי עלמא שרי ei
sharei lekulei alma sharei if it's permissible it's permissible for everybody. אי
אסור לכולי עלמא אסור ei assur lekulei alma assur if it's forbidden
it's forbidden for everybody. שאני רב הונא דעדינין דעתיה. shani Rav Huna
de-adinin datei. Rav Huna was different that he was very finicky, so
there's gotta be a better word than finicky. אסטניס, istenis, what's the
translation of אסטניס? istenis? What? Not... no no אסטניס istenis is just
like aesthetically or
what... fastidious. Fastidious, that's the word. Fastidious. So anyway,
כשרות kashrut was totally kosher. For him it was just gross or
he was fastidious, he didn't like eating that red, you know, that
red stuff. He liked his meat well done, he didn't like to
see that red juicy stuff so he gave it to his to
his attendant. But that was just his own personal taste
issues, halachically it was permissible. So now it's important, now we have
an opposing voice to Shmuel that says that even those juices are
permissible. So let's keep on going.
Yes?
Couldn't the meat on the bread just because their bread wasn't like
ours, theirs was a pita bread so it was a big round
piece.
Ah, so it was easier to serve as like of a cutting
board. Ah, that's interesting. That could be, okay, thanks. Okay,
רבא Rava and now we're going to have another opinion that argues
on Shmuel. רבא אכיל ליה Rava achil lei he would like to
he ate this and you see there's a little letter by רבא
Rava and it says חמרא דבשרא chamra devasra he called it the
wine of the meat. Oh, the wonderful red juices that come off
the meat. So he basically said once you kosher it maybe also
once you roast it if whatever the requisite amount of time is
for doing it, right, then it is considered to be acceptable. Now
again, presumably we are talking here about roasting because if we were
talking about koshering with salt and then you cooked it, if there
was concern that the salt didn't get it all out then we
wouldn't let you cook it because then it would again go out
and come back in. So the only scenarios that the גמרא Gemara
could reasonably consider that there's still some blood left are roasting. Because
roasting you get the meat edible, you get it cooked, and you
could say there's meat left in, but what went in stayed in
what came out came out and fell out. So here the גמרא's
Gemara, assumption is, so do we normally assume the roasting process gets
out all of the blood or not? And that was very much
an issue that came up in yesterday's דף. daf. So here what
is the story about the red juices that come out after roasting?
Blood or not blood? And here the גמרא's Gemara saying at that
stage it's not blood, it's just considered like juice and gravy or
whatever but all the stuff that's halachically blood, I assume that the
reason it's red is that it actually is has blood in it,
is that right? Does anybody know?
Yes, it's surplus of blood.
Okay, that's what I assumed. But anyway, but might be more of
a halachic question that once you did the roasting process and if
you left it on, you know the גמרא Gemara just earlier was
discussing when you know it's done, but whenever you know it's done
then anything left is at that stage no longer...
and it is a relatively small amount of blood compared to the
amount that's gone through the arteries and the heart. Okay. Shmuel's theory
about this, the difference between
thick and thin
is pretty reasonable,
you're saying, right?
Well what's what's the theory? It's blood or it's not blood?
Well no, I mean oh you mean oh you mean because that
seems that it's not just making a... he makes a halachic line
and say once you do the process and anything left halachically isn't
blood, then fine. But if you're saying that no there might be
some blood left,
so what does he think the red stuff is, the thin red
stuff if it's not blood? Yeah, I don't know. Red juice. And
but you're right, for him he can't he would not be able
to admit that the red stuff, the thin red stuff has a
blood content to it. You are correct, yes.
And they didn't know about blood circulation anyway, so this is all
based on...
right, I mean they did know that there was blood in the
meat, I mean that's why you salt the meat so I mean
you know,
I never get what that means that they didn't know there was
such a thing as blood circulation.
It was discovered in the 16th century.
I know what that means but I meant
before.
They thought it was just there, they didn't understand that it...
they saw veins, they saw arteries, they saw there was a lot
of blood in them, I don't I don't know. Yeah. All right,
let's go on. Yes. Down or up? Where are we? אמר רב
נחמן אמר שמואל Amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel אין מניחין כלי תחת
בשר עד שיכלה כל מראה אדמומית שבה. ein manichin kli tachat basar
ad sheyichleh kol mareh admumit shebah. Now
here again we get about, this was the בי דוגי bei dugi
that we mentioned yesterday, always reminds me of Doogie Howser.
Okay, so you are roasting your meat and you want to catch
all the yummy meat juices that fall off. of the gravy, but
the part is that blood is coming out at the same time.
So you remember the גמרא Gemara yesterday said how do you deal
with the blood that runs off? Well, that blood is, you know,
on the surface, okay, so it goes to the bottom, so you
can take the gravy off of the surface. Here the גמרא Gemara
is dealing with that problem again. So we're saying you have to
wait till all that as it's over the fire and the juices
start coming out that there's no longer any red in, you know,
reddish color in the juices. Then you know no longer blood is
coming out and now you can catch the juices and the gravy.
But before that, as blood is coming out, that's a problem because
it'll mix into the gravy that you catch. Okay, עד שיכלה כל
מראה אדמומית ad sheyichleh kol mareh admumit until all the redness is
over שבו. shebo. מנא ידעינן? mena yadeinan? Where do you know? How
can you tell? You know, obviously what, you can't be looking at
all the different juices that are coming out. How are you going
to see?
So מנא ידעינן? mena yadeinan?
Look at the ground.
Okay, well, maybe, but you know, it's all falling in different places.
I mean, you've got a whole big thing over the fire. What?
Yeah. מר זוטרא משמיה דרב פפא אמר משיעלה תימרתו. Mar Zutra mishmei
deRav Papa amar misheya'aleh timrato.
When the smoke goes up. What does this mean? So רש"י Rashi
says it means that the, he has two explanations. One is that
the meat itself is smoking. The other explanation רש"י Rashi says is
that the embers underneath the meat, so as long as the blood
is dripping on it, that keeps them from smoking. But after the
blood stops dripping and it's just the juices that are dripping, I
guess it starts smoking. I don't know what he says there. Yeah,
I was going to say, right, isn't it that when things are
dripping, my instinct is the opposite. There's a little hole in the
bottom of my pot, then the oven gets all smoky because, yeah,
so I don't know. Anyways, somehow when the smoke starts coming up,
then you know the blood has stopped coming down. מתיב רב אשי.
metiv Rav Ashi. Said רב אשי, Rav Ashi, דילמא מתתא מטא עילא
לא מטא. dilma mitata mata ila lo mata. Maybe the bottom is
roasted, the top is not roasted. You know, so meaning how do
you know? You know, maybe this effect if you are roasting two
pieces of meat one on top of the other, so maybe the
bottom one is because it's near the fire, it itself is being
smoky, but the top, the top that's further away from the fire,
blood is still coming down. And how do you know that you've
got, you're
not turning it around on your spit?
Apparently not.
So how do you know that all of the red has come
out, all the blood has come out?
אלא אמר רב אשי, ela amar Rav Ashi, לית ליה תקנתא אלא
משדי בה תרתי גללי מלחא. leit leh takanta ela mishdei bah tarti
galalei milcha. The only way to solve the problem, and this is
more like what we said yesterday, is okay, sometimes you will get
some blood that's mixed up with your juices. Yesterday it suggested you
could solve it by just taking off the top layer of the
gravy and the blood would stay at the bottom. Here there's a
different solution. You take two mounds of salt, you put them in
your dish. Apparently the blood is drawn to the salt and therefore
we assume it gets absorbed and contained within the salt and what
you take out is just the juices. Pretty shocking, like nobody would
ever think about doing this nowadays, right? Meat juice mixed with salt?
Right, it's a derived blood. You know, it's really the blood that's
coming out, although תוספות Tosafot based on a גמרא Gemara in כריתות,
Keritot, right, תוספות Tosafot although the רמב"ם Rambam doesn't really quote this
גמרא, Gemara. תוספות Tosafot brings up a גמרא Gemara in כריתות Keritot
that says that once the blood has been cooked, it's only דרבנן.
derabbanan. Although the רמב"ם Rambam doesn't, yeah,
although the רמב"ם Rambam doesn't bring that up. But still, you know,
that that's sufficient that the blood and also you wonder if it's
all coming out as a result of heat, why isn't the taste
of the blood mixing with the taste of the juices? So even
if you draw the actual blood, the עין ayin into the salt,
how does the juice become permitted? Let's say that there's so much
of the other juices, it's בטל. batel. Anyway, תוספות Tosafot basically says
because he quotes the בה"ג Behag who says this is only two
mounds. Too much salt or too little salt won't do the job.
It has to be this exact amount of salt. And of course,
since we don't know how to exactly estimate, so we can't rely
on it. Okay, if you want to show you this, look at
the last line of תוספות Tosafot on our דף. daf. So he
says
two lines from the bottom on
ק"ב ע"א. kuf bet amud aleph. וסימנא שפירש בהלכות גדולות דדווקא נקט
תרי גללי, vesimana sheperish beHalachot Gedolot dedavka nakat terei galalei, only exactly
two. אבל הרבה מלח פוסק כח הדם. aval harbeh melach posek koach
hadam. But if it's more than two, it stops the power of
blood. You'd think that's a good thing, but it probably means it
dissolves the blood and makes the blood mixed into the gravy and
doesn't pull the blood to it or
whatever. ואין אנו בקיאין בדבר. ve'ein anu beki'in badavar. That is, by
the way, the Ashkenazi phrase for what I call keep it simple
stupid is ואין אנו בקיאין בדבר. ve'ein anu beki'in badavar. We're not
expert to make these
distinctions. Okay, לא להרבות ולא למעט, lo leharbot velo lema'et, not to
do too much or too little. So therefore we cannot do this
at all.
Okay, and it's all predicated on the idea that look, you're taking
the whole idea of koshering is you're taking blood out of the
meat. Right, but the meat is kosher, it has blood in it,
but that's the process. Maybe this is an extension of the process.
Oh, so we allow that to be considered to be still the
process of separating the two, separating the blood that actually came out
from the juices. Maybe, maybe, although you know, again, in my mind
the question still is that why is it not some transfer of
the taste? Because why the blood that's in the meat, it wouldn't
transfer the taste to the meat? Yeah, but there we say
that usually we say when once the blood comes out, that's when
it becomes
אסור.
assur. and you slowly pour out the gravy on the top. So
the salt keeps the blood at the bottom, keeps it in the
salt, and then the gravy, and we said yesterday the blood is
heavier, stays at the bottom, and if you slowly pour out or
scoop out the gravy at the top, then you can remove the
gravy without getting the blood. But of course we do not do
that. We are not concerned about that if it's in a big
pot, that's a big thing, and the salt is at the bottom.
אמרי רב אחא בריה דרב איקא לרב אשי: Amrei Rav Acha brei
de-Rav Ika le-Rav Ashi: ומי אמר שמואל הכי? U-mi amar Shmuel hachi?
Did שמואל Shmuel really say that? Because שמואל Shmuel דגיליסא de-gili-sa that
it was permissible to do this. Remember שמואל Shmuel didn't mention the
salt. שמואל Shmuel just basically said
that once the blood stops coming out,
you can then, you know, when it stops looking red, then you
can catch the gravy. ומי אמר שמואל הכי? U-mi amar Shmuel hachi?
Did שמואל Shmuel really say this? והאמר שמואל חיקרא דחיתכא ליה בשרא
אסור למיכליה. Ve-ha-amar Shmuel chikra de-chitcha lei besara asur le-michlei. שמואל Shmuel
was the one that said that the red stuff that comes out
on the bread is forbidden to eat. Now why is that a
problem? Because he presumably says from there we see that שמואל Shmuel
holds that even after meat is fully roasted, it can still contain
blood, right? Because that's שמואל's Shmuel whole point. Even if you cut
roasted meat, the red stuff is still blood and it's still forbidden.
So if that's true, how could that same שמואל Shmuel say that
after the red stops coming out when you're roasting it, you can
catch the gravy? Why aren't we concerned that some of those juices
contains the blood if שמואל Shmuel himself says, you know, that it
can sometimes contain the blood? Now there seems that there could be
an answer. שמואל's Shmuel not saying it will always be blood that
will be left. If red thick stuff comes out, it's blood, right?
That was what we said before. So here
we say
if you're roasting it and there's no red stuff coming out, you're
okay, then all the blood came out. If red stuff does come
out, then it's a problem, right? That would be a simple answer.
But the גמרא Gemara is asking this question. Before שמואל Shmuel says
that even after roasted there still could be blood in it, how
here can he let you catch the gravy and not be concerned
that there is still blood? So let's see. So the גמרא Gemara
says: שאני התם דאגב דוחקא דסכינא פליט. Shani hatam de-agav duchka de-sakina
palit.
So it gives another answer. Interestingly, roasting might not get out all
the blood, but there will be blood that will still get deeply
buried in that won't be accessible by roasting, but when you use
the pressure of the knife, that could get it out. So therefore
he's saying it is possible that in the roasting process blood stops
coming out and you can catch the gravy, but it doesn't mean
that all the blood is out. There's blood that's trapped in the
meat that will come out when you cut it. Okay, so this
is שמואל. Shmuel. שמואל Shmuel says roasting you eat the meat but
you can't assume all the blood has come out. And therefore red
juices that come out afterwards are a problem. The alternative is to
say no, roasting we do assume all of the blood comes out,
anything left behind is not halachically blood and that's how we rule.
And therefore if you roast it whatever the requisite amount of time
is, anything left is no longer considered blood. But if you want
to actually catch the juices while the blood is coming out, then
you have to figure out how to do it so you're not
also catching the blood. Yes, Charlie.
So but so if I bite into a piece of rare meat
some blood is going to ooze out. Right. By that opinion I
can't eat...
No, you are allowed to eat, you are allowed to eat, it's
a good question, you are allowed to eat
raw meat as I said, as long as it hasn't פירש. peirash.
What comes out in your mouth is presumably already considered like part
of the eating process and not considered separate. Okay, but if you
were cutting a piece of raw meat, you could put the raw
meat straight in your mouth חס ושלום, chas ve-shalom, but the juices
that ran off, that would be...
you can't tear it off with your hands and
put it in your mouth is what you're saying? If juices came
off, then you couldn't. Right. Down. Okay. Okay, now so now the
גמרא Gemara. continues. Now we get back to, so we keep on
sort of going back and forth from different topics, you know, so
yesterday we had a lot about the blood and the liver, now
we come back to the blood and the roasting, and the roasting,
you know, certainly allows you to eat the meat, does it get
all the blood out or not? Is this major debate about רב
Rav and שמואל Shmuel and whatever about the story about the red
juices. But now we get back to what we sort of more
started today with, which is saltiness, מליח הרי הוא כרותח. maliach harei
hu ke-roteach. So there's a lot of moving back and forth. So
now and thankfully we have a very big תוספות Tosafot so we're
going to finish the דף daf today. Now let's get back to
the story about saltiness. We leave removing blood and roasting and we
get back to saltiness as a transfer of taste. Let's take a
look. אמר רב נחמן: Amar Rav Nachman: דגים ועופות שמלחן זה עם
זה. Dagim ve-ofot she-melachan zeh im zeh. You are salting your fish
and your birds together for different reasons. Your fish, your birds you're
salting to get out the blood, to kosher. Your fish you're salting
because you want to make herring or you want to make whatever
you make by salted fish. Okay, but they're all on the same
platform and you're salting them all at the same time. Okay, now
what's the problem? The birds, the blood is coming out. Okay, and
you got fish here. So the blood, we're concerned is going to
come out of
the bird... Now in general you can salt multiple pieces of meat
together. Why am I not concerned if I'm salting five chickens together
and even if they're one on top of the other like you
know if it's on the board it's a slanted board so the
blood runs off. Right, if they're all at the same on the
same row, you could say it's all running off, it's not running
into one another although you could still maybe be concerned about a
little bit getting caught on the side. But I can even have
multiple rows and salt it all and the blood is running off
and the blood from the top row is running through the bottom
row but I'm not concerned that the bottom row is absorbing. Why
not? That's what this huge תוספות Tosafot is about. Why not? Okay?
Why not? I'm going to tell you some possibilities but we are
concerned that if it's birds and fish, the fish will absorb. Why
am I not concerned if it's birds and birds or birds and
meat or whatever? So there's a couple of principles that are at
play here. One is איידי דטריד למפלט לא בלע. Aidi d'tarid l'miflat
lo bala. Since the meat is busy spewing out, it's, you know,
it can't absorb. So therefore since everything is salted and it's also
spewing out its own blood, it's not absorbing other blood.
That is not a sufficient principle because תוספות Tosafot is concerned about,
well, if therefore if the meat at the bottom, if I did
it a minute before the meat at the top and it finishes
a minute before, why is it absorbing the blood from the meat
on top? So we have other principles. Other principles is well one
is a variation of that. It's not only if it's busy spewing
out its blood, it's even if it's busy spewing out its juices.
So the bottom stuff are spitting out even its juices even after
it finishes the blood and therefore and therefore it won't absorb the
taste from the and therefore it won't absorb the taste from the
top. Or it maybe it does absorb the taste from the top
but it keeps on spewing it out because it's spewing out its
own
juices which are fine. Then the other principle is a variation of
that which is דם משרק שריק. Dam mishrak sharik. That blood is
very slippery. So blood glides off and doesn't stick. Okay? But as
we're going to see, fish are going to be an exception because
fish are considered A. not to be spewing out their own blood,
fish finish spewing out their juices before the meat spews out its
blood and because their surface is very absorbent. So you cannot those
purpose those different sort of ways in which we say that the
case of כשר kasher is okay don't work for the fish. But
basically this תוספות Tosafot is trying to figure out a couple of
different ways to explain the common practice that we כשר kasher, meat
together and we can assume that the blood doesn't get absorbed and
why is the גמרא only concerned about it by the fish? So
let's take a look at this גמרא. Okay? דגים ועופות שמלחן זה
עם זה, Dagim v'ofot shemalchan zeh im zeh,
you salted them together, אסור, assur, forbidden. היכי דמי, Heichi dami,
what's the case? אי בכלי שאינו מנוקב, Ei bikli she'eino menukav, if
it is a vessel that doesn't have a hole at the bottom.
I gave an example of a slanted board, but let's say you're
doing it actually in a in a pot, in a vessel. And
if it has no hole in the bottom, so all the blood
is collecting at the bottom of the vessel and everything is sitting
in the blood, אפילו עופות ועופות נמי אסורי. afilu ofot v'ofot nami
assiri. So then you can't do it even with birds and birds,
even the same bird. Right? You have to כשר, kasher you have
to כשר either on top of something that has holes in it
or on a slanted board so the blood runs away. If it
sits in the blood, then we're going to say it's going to
re-absorb its own blood. So that would be a problem even with
that. אי בכלי מנוקב, Ei bikli menukav, and if it has holes
or on like the slanted board, אפילו דגים ועופות נמי שרי, afilu
dagim v'ofot nami shari, let it be permissible even with fish, let
it all run off. So the גמרא says לעולם בכלי מנוקב, Le'olam
bikli menukav, it has holes. ודגים, V'dagim, but fish, משום דרפו קרמייהו,
mishum derafu karmaihu, because their shell, their outer surface is very soft,
very absorbent, קדמי ופלטי, kadmi ufalti, they finish getting rid of spewing
out their juices before the birds finish. ועופות קמיטי, V'ofot kmiti, and
the birds initially sort of are
what's the word kmit? It's like
not absorb like wrinkled essentially, meaning it holds back. Hard to translate
to this. Tight.
Tight. Thank you. Okay, it holds back its blood and so it
takes time for the blood to come out. בתר דנייחו דגים, Batar
d'naihu dagim, and only after the fish finish getting rid of their
juices, פלטי עופות, palti ofot, then the blood comes out of the
bird, והדר בלעי מיניהו, v'hadar bali mineihu, and then it absorbs the
blood. So if you had the
fish on top and the
birds on the bottom it would be okay. If the fish were
on top, yes, actually that's a good point. If the fish were
on top and the birds were on bottom and it was a
slanted board, that would be okay. But the point here is is
that so the גמרא uses these two ideas. Number one, they're no
longer getting rid of their stuff, and number two, their skin is
very
absorbent. And that allows תוספות Tosafot, to say that the reason that
by birds and birds it's okay is because number one, we could
say they continue to spew at the same time and even if
not spewing out blood but spewing out juices is enough to prevent
the blood from being absorbed, any blood that's absorbed gets re-spit out.
And it also allows תוספות just to say that maybe even without
that because they don't have the soft shell of fish, the blood
just glides right off of the other of the other bird, but
it will not glide off of the shell of the fish. And
the fish because their shell is absorbent, shell, whatever outer layer is
absorbent. Because they are done spewing off sooner, they are open to
absorb the blood that is coming out of the bird.
Questions on those first questions?
What? Oh, he does have a lot of different scenarios and a
lot of different possibilities. Okay, now the גמרא says and he has
to deal with a lot of things about actual practice. Let's just
read one more line. רב מרי בר רחל Rav Mari bar Rachel
אימלח ליה imlech lei בשר שחוטה basar shchuta בהדי bahadi בשר טריפה.
basar trefa.
He salted pieces of meat together and one of them was a
טריפה, trefa, presumably unwittingly. What happened? He gets two pieces of meat
from the butcher, he salts them, and then an announcement goes out,
"Oh, that other, you know, that second piece of meat, I just
found a טריפה trefa in the cow, that's טריפה." trefa. And he
now has salted them together, kosher meat and טריפה trefa meat. Okay,
אתא לקמיה דרבא. ata lekamei deRava. So now we have learned that
if the juices transfer, it could be a problem. Of course, we've
also learned that if you're salting things at the same time and
they're both presumably birds or both pieces of meat, they don't transfer
blood. So he came to רבא, Rava, so רבא Rava said, אמר
ליה, amar lei, הטמאים, hatme'im,
it says these are what is not kosher to you, לאסור lesor
צירן tsiran ורוטבן verotban וקיפה שלהן. vekippa shelahen.
Not only is the meat of a טריפה trefa not kosher, but
even the juices of a טריפה trefa is not kosher. And the
other things are like the goop in the pot, but the real
חידוש chiddush is that the juices of a טריפה trefa are just
as not kosher as the meat of the טריפה trefa itself. So,
when do we say if you're salting things together they don't absorb,
salting let's say pieces of meat together, they don't absorb blood, because
blood we say has this quality of being very slippery and will
glide right off. But here the problem from the טריפה tref piece
of meat wasn't that it absorbed the blood of the טריפה tref
piece of meat, but it had absorbed the juices of the טריפה
tref piece of meat. So because it was salted together, the other
piece did absorb the juices. And we will continue tomorrow, but here
again you see the big תוספות, you see the two basic principles
implicit in this גמרא. By the fish it mentioned that they finished
spewing out, so it's the spewing which prevents absorbing. And by the
meat, the point was that it wasn't blood. Had it been blood,
it wouldn't have absorbed, because that's salting two pieces of meat together.
But because, so that has to do with the quality of blood
being defined as slippery and preventing its absorption. But because it's the
juices of the piece of meat of the non-kosher, that does get
absorbed. The final question is, who needs this פסוק pasuk about to
forbid the juices of the meat? Why isn't it just the general
principle that טעם כעיקר, ta'am ke'ikar, taste is like the thing itself?
So it might be that the juice of the meat does not
have the same taste as the meat itself and you can't use
טעם כעיקר ta'am ke'ikar and you need this special פסוק pasuk to
tell you that the juice of the meat is treated like the
meat and is just as forbidden as the meat of a non-kosher
item. Okay.